Thanks for joining. Today we're talking about how to actually evaluate a
retrieval-augmented generation system once you've built one.
Most teams start by eyeballing a handful of answers, which catches the
obvious failures but misses everything else.
The first thing to separate is retrieval quality from generation quality.
These fail independently and need different fixes.
For retrieval, the standard metrics are recall at k and mean reciprocal
rank, measured against a labeled set of query to relevant passage pairs.
If recall at k is low, no amount of prompt engineering on the generation
side will fix the system, because the evidence was never retrieved.
For generation, we care about groundedness, whether every claim in the
answer is actually supported by the retrieved passages.
An answer can be fluent and confident and still be ungrounded if the model
fills a gap in the retrieved evidence with something from its own training.
A practical way to check groundedness at scale is to use a second model as
a judge, scoring correctness, completeness, and clarity separately.
The judge should always be shown the same evidence the generator was
shown, otherwise you're grading against the judge's own knowledge instead.
We've also found it useful to log every tool call the system makes, not
just the final answer, because that's what makes failures debuggable.
When a run fails, you want to see which sub-queries were issued, what came
back, and where the answer diverged from the evidence.
One limitation worth naming: automated judges tend to be lenient on
completeness and stricter on correctness, so track them separately.
Running the same fixed question set after every prompt change is what
turns this from vibes into an actual regression test.
That's the core loop. Happy to take questions.